<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A most strange and rare example of the iust iudgement of God executed vpon a lewde and wicked coniurer the .xvij. day of Ianuarie. M.D.Lxxvij. In the parish church of S. Mary Oueris in Southwark, in the presence of diuers credible [and] honest persons</title>
            <author>Pembroke, Simon.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1577</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09279</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19593</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112861</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848103</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848103</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13181</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09279)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13181)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1637:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A most strange and rare example of the iust iudgement of God executed vpon a lewde and wicked coniurer the .xvij. day of Ianuarie. M.D.Lxxvij. In the parish church of S. Mary Oueris in Southwark, in the presence of diuers credible [and] honest persons</title>
                  <author>Pembroke, Simon.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Henrie Bennyman,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1577]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Simon Pembroke.</note>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁶.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13181:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 68 -->
            <p>¶ A moſt ſtrange and rare example of the iuſt iudgement of God executed vpon a lewde and wicked Coniurer the .xvij. day of Ianuarie .M.D.Lxxvij. In the pariſh church of S. Mary Ouerie in Southwark, in the preſence of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers credible &amp; honeſt perſons.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>¶<hi>Imprinted at London, by Henrie Bennyman.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:13181:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 69 -->
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:13181:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 69 -->REmember mortal man how time doth paſſe,</l>
            <l>and know likewiſe, al humain fleſh is gras:</l>
            <l>For time at le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumes the ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt oke,</l>
            <l>So death at laſt muſt ſtrike the greuous ſtroke:</l>
            <l>Though luſtie youth do pleaſant beautie beare</l>
            <l>Yet youth to age in tract of time doth we are.</l>
            <l>The pleſant flour that bears the freſheſt hue</l>
            <l>The graſſe that grows ſo grene in ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer tide</l>
            <l>The pinching colde hir colour dothe ſubdue,</l>
            <l>So that hir beautie cannot long abide:</l>
            <l>Euen ſo the ſtate of mortall man depends,</l>
            <l>Whoſe life to theſe may well compared be,</l>
            <l>To daye the powers aboue our life defends:</l>
            <l>To morrowe deade full oftentimes we ſee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </l>
            <l>Therfore ſtill liue as though thou ſhuldeſt dye,</l>
            <l>Thy ſoule to ſaue from ſo greate ieopardye.</l>
            <l>If mortall man woulde weigh his ſtate aright,</l>
            <l>And ſhun the ſubtill ſnares of falſe delight,</l>
            <l>Eſteming them to be ſo fraile and vaine,</l>
            <l>As nothing elſe maye ſooner bring our paine:</l>
            <l>He woulde (no doubt) his courſe direct aright,</l>
            <l>And haue thoſe ſhewes no longer in his ſight.</l>
            <l>And though our nature be ſo weake and frayle,</l>
            <l>As any one attempt may ſoone auayle,</l>
            <l>No doubt but if with zeale we call for grace,</l>
            <l>We ſhall eſchew ſuche lewde attempts apace.</l>
            <l>The ſygnes and ſhewes that dayly doe appeere,</l>
            <l>In coaſtes abroade and in our countrie here,</l>
            <l>May well a warnyng be vnto vs all,</l>
            <l>To ſhun the ſynne that we be chargde withall,</l>
            <l>Let vs example take of holy writ,</l>
            <l>Wheron ech chriſten man ſhuld ground his wit,</l>
            <l>Howe God (for ſynne) in his diſpleaſed yre,</l>
            <l>Conſumed <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorre</hi> with fyre.</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:13181:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 70 -->In theſe our dayes it may be eke regarded,</l>
            <l>How dyuers countreys for ſinne are rewarded.</l>
            <l>Let vs therefore by them example take,</l>
            <l>And from our ſinnes at length let vs awake,</l>
            <l>Which God of his mercy graunt for to be,</l>
            <l>That we in ioyes euerlaſting may ſee</l>
            <l>The heuenly ſhew of his moſte glorious face,</l>
            <l>Pronouncing ioys to them that cal for grace,</l>
            <trailer>
               <hi>AMEN.</hi> 
               <figure/>
            </trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:13181:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 70 -->
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the Synnes of Man are innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and dyuerſe, gentle Reader, ſo the plagues &amp; pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhmentes of God are ſundrye: and he ſharpely ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth manye, that wee the reſydue myghte the better bee warned. And though he ſuffer and beare with our wicked deedes and dealings a while, yet without amendement, and oure repentaunce, hee will ſtryke at laſte, with ſo heauie and greuous a ſtroke that our frayle bodyes may not nor ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not ſuſtayn his heauy hande. Let therefore euery true Chriſtian enter into his own heart, &amp; conſyder how mercyfull God is, how he warneth vs, howe he ſpareth vs, and gyueth daily examples for our amendement, how he plageth the offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dor, thoughe mercifull to a great ſorte of ſinners.
<pb facs="tcp:13181:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 71 -->
If we woulde conſyder this tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie worlde howe tickle it ſtandeth, howe vncertayne the lyfe of man is, howe we can aſſure vnto our ſelues nothyng certayne but death, howe our toyles, our laboures, oure cares, our inuentions, oure pollicies and ſubtilties paſſe with our mortall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies: vndoubtedly the verie horrour of our conſciences, woulde cauſe vs to bee more carefull to refrayne oure naturall bodies from ſuch filthy, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable and abhominable liuing, as they are moſt prone and ready to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe and imbrace: yea it woulde ſo moue our myndes to deuotion, that therby the vayn induſtries, lewd at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptes, and wycked imaginations of our hearte myght be altered and chaunged to true Religion, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantneſſe of Faith, and to true and ſyncere dealyng one with an other. Let vs therfore ſearche and examine
<pb facs="tcp:13181:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 71 -->
our ſelues, and lyke the loſte ſonne come home &amp; crie Abba father, and then vndoubtedly, with ſpreaded ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, hee will bee ready to receiue vs to his great mercye, whereas on the contrarie hee will ſhewe hymſelfe a fierce and terrible god, pronouncing a moſt ſharpe iudgement vppon the offendor, yea he wil ſteale vpon him on a day whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he loketh not for him, and in an houre that he is not ware of, and ſhall hewe him in peeces, and giue him his portion with the hipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, where there ſhall be weepyng and gnaſhing of teethe. After which ſorte, God in his iuſtice, ſtroke the perſone of whom we nowe ſpeake: who maye well bee a myrrour and ſpectacle to vs all, that we knowing and ſeeyng the ende of hys wycked life, may renewe the olde man graf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed in our harts, glorifying our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father whiche is in Heauen,
<pb facs="tcp:13181:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 72 -->
whiche God graunte of his mercye. Amen.</p>
            <p>The ſeuenteenth daye of Ianua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie this preſente yeare of our Lorde God a thouſand fiue hundred ſeuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and ſixe, one Simon Pembroke dwelling in Sainct Georges pariſh in Southwark, beyng co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uented be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ordinarie iudge of that place as veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ſuſpected to be a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurer, and the proces beeing ſerued vpon him to appeare in the Pariſhe Churche of Sainct Marie Ouery, at the Court there vſually holden by the ſayde Iudge, to aunſwere vnto ſuche obiections, as he myghte bee charged wythal, touching his diuel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhe trade, and to receyue condygne puniſhment if he were founde culpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble therein: albeit ſomewhat ſickely before, as it muſt truly be confeſſed, neuertheleſſe choſing rather to come than to vſe any excuſe of abſence,
<pb facs="tcp:13181:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 72 -->
he fayled not at his appoynted daye to appeare, ſhewing him ſelfe ready in euery reſpect to cleare him ſelfe of all ſuche matters as ſhould or might in any wiſe be obiected againſt him, ſaying, that he had gret wrong to be troubled for any ſuche falſe ſurmyſe, Wherevpon comming to a Proctor of the Arches, &amp; mynding to retaine hym to bee of his counſell touchyng the defence of the obiections layde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, being refuſed by the ſaid Proctor, &amp; with his fee in his hande, the Iudge comming into the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, he ſank down ſodeynly amongſt them ſtarke deade, not hauing ſpace or grace to ſaye once, the Lord haue mercie vpon me: to the great amaze of al the ſtanders by. The Iudge ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what had chaunced, and that by no meanes his lyfe coulde be recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, he commaunded that he ſhoulde be ſerched, to the intent that if he had
<pb facs="tcp:13181:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 73 -->
money or other chardge about him, it might not bee embeſelled, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to his poore wife, beeing there preſent, lamenting hir late huſbande in moſte pitifull ſorte, whiche done there were found about him certain diueliſhe and wicked bookes of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuration, a peece of tinne with a pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture engraued, &amp; a lttle blacke ſticke like vnto Iette, aboute two inches long, with other toies, inſtrumentes no doubt of his diueliſh arte.</p>
            <p>Wherfore let this iuſt &amp; ſodain exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of gods iudgement, be a terror vnto thoſe, that ſetting apart y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy &amp; great mercy of our heauenly father, haue practiſed this or the like wicked trade, &amp; let al other that are infected with any notable crime, as no doubte none of vs can excuſe our ſelues, take example by thys deade carkas, whoſe manner of lyfe as it was abhomynable, and odyous in
<pb facs="tcp:13181:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 73 -->
the ſighte of god, ſo the order of hys death no leſſe fearful, and terrible in the ſight of men. I ſay after ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny warnyngs, let vs not be ſenſleſſe as bruite beaſtes, neither lette vs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre our repentaunce vntill to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, leaſt at midnight, or at the dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of the day our time be ſhorte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, whereby to late, wee are to call for repentaunce: but while we haue time and ſpace, let vs call for mercy, that we may aſſure our ſelues of his comfortable promiſſe, which is, that at what tyme ſoeuer a ſynner dothe repent him of his ſinnes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of his harte, I will put all his wickednes out of my remembrance, and ſo glorifying him in this life, we may bee partakers of the heauenlye ioyes, prepared for his elected, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che God graunte, for his ſonne Ieſu Chriſtes ſake. Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
